window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Discrete_Mathematics - Functions — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Functions — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>\\(g(. )\\) is a function from \\(A\\) to \\(B\\), \\(f(. )\\) is a function from \\(B\\) to \\(C\\), and their composition defined as \\(f(g(. ))\\) is a mapping from \\(A\\) to \\(C\\). <br>If \\(f(. )\\) and \\(f(g(. ))\\) are onto (surjective) functions, which ONE of the following is TRUE about the function \\(g(. )\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(g(. )\\) must be an onto (surjective) function.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(g(. )\\) must be a one-to-one (injective) function.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(g(. )\\) must be a bijective function, that is, both one-to-one and onto.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(g(. )\\) is not required to be a one-to-one or onto function.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(g(. )\\) is not required to be a one-to-one or onto function.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460073/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-7#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(A \\) and \\(B \\) be non-empty finite sets such that there exist one-to-one and onto functions (i) from \\(A \\) to \\(B \\) and (ii) from \\(A \\times A \\) to \\(A \\cup B \\). The number of possible values of \\(|A| \\) is ___ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "2",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422820/gate-cse-2024-set-1-question-22#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(f: \\mathbb{R} \\rightarrow \\mathbb{R} \\) be a function such that \\(f(x)=\\max \\left\\{x, x^3\\right\\}, x \\in \\mathbb{R} \\), where \\(\\mathbb{R} \\) is the set of all real numbers. The set of all points where \\(f(x) \\) is NOT differentiable is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(-1,1,2 \\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(-2,-1,1 \\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(0,1 \\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(-1,0,1\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(-1,0,1\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422841/gate-cse-2024-set-1-question-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Let \\( f:A\\rightarrow B\\) be an onto (or surjective) function, where \\(A\\)  and \\(B\\) are nonempty\nsets. Define an equivalence relation \\( \\sim \\)  on the set \\(A\\) as<br> \\( a_1\\sim a_2 \\text{ if } f(a_1)=f(a_2),\\)  <br> where \\( a_1, a_2  \\in A\\) . Let \\( \\varepsilon =\\{[x]:x \\in A\\}\\)  be the set of all the equivalence classes\nunder \\( \\sim \\). Define a new mapping \\( F: \\varepsilon \\rightarrow B\\)  as  <br>\\(F([x]) = f(x),\\) for all the equivalence classes \\([x]\\) in \\(  \\varepsilon\\)<br>Which of the following statements is/are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>F is NOT well-defined.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>F is an onto (or surjective) function.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>F is a one-to-one (or injective) function.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>F is a bijective function.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>B.</b> <p>F is an onto (or surjective) function.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>F is a one-to-one (or injective) function.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>F is a bijective function.</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399272/gate-cse-2023-question-39#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following is the closed form for the generating function of the sequence \\( \\{a_n \\}_{n \\geq 0}\\) defined below?<br>\\(a_n= \\left \\{ \\begin{matrix}\nn+1, &amp;n  \\text{ is odd}  \\\\\n1,&amp;  \\text{otherwise}\n\\end{matrix} \\right.\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{x(1+x^2)}{(1-x^2)^2}+\\frac{1}{1-x}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{x(3-x^2)}{(1-x^2)^2}+\\frac{1}{1-x}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{2x}{(1-x^2)^2}+\\frac{1}{1-x}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{x}{(1-x^2)^2}+\\frac{1}{1-x}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{x(1+x^2)}{(1-x^2)^2}+\\frac{1}{1-x}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371910/Gate-cse-2022-question-26#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following sets, where \\(n\\geq 2\\):<br><br>S1: Set of all nxn matrices with entries from the set \\(\\{a, b, c\\}\\)<br>\nS2: Set of all functions from the set\\(\\{0,1,2,...,n^2-1\\}\\) to the set \\(\\{0, 1, 2 \\}\\)<br><br>\nWhich of the following choice(s) is/are correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>There does not exist a bijection from S1 to S2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>There exists a surjection from S1 to S2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>There exists a bijection from S1 to S2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>There does not exist an injection from S1 to S2</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>B.</b> <p>There exists a surjection from S1 to S2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>There exists a bijection from S1 to S2</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357529/gate-cse-2021-set-2-question-11#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>If the ordinary generating function of a sequence \\(\\{a_{n}\\}_{n=0}^{\\infty} \\;  is \\;  \\frac{1+z}{(1-z)^{3}}\\) then \\(a_{3}-a_{0}\\) is equal to ______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "15",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118392/gate2017-2-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>If \\(g(x)=1-x\\) and \\(h(x)=\\frac{x}{x-1}\\), then \\(\\frac{g(h(x))}{h(g(x))}\\) is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{h(x)}{g(x)}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{-1}{x}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{g(x)}{h(x)}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{x}{(1-x)^{2}}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{h(x)}{g(x)}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8025/gate2015-1-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Let A be a finite set having \\(x\\) elements and let B be a finite set having \\(y\\) elements. What is the number of distinct functions mapping B into A. <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(x^{y}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^{(x+y)}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(y^{x}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(y ! /(y-x) !\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(x^{y}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/54987/isro2014-50\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider the set of all functions f:{0,1,...,2014}\\(\\rightarrow\\){0,1...,2014} such that f(f(i))=i, for 0\\(\\leq\\)i\\(\\leq\\)2014 . Consider the following statements. <br>\nP. For each such function it must be the case that for every i, f(i) = i, <br>\nQ. For each such function it must be the case that for some i,f(i) = i, <br>\nR. Each such function must be onto. <br>\nWhich one of the following is CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>P, Q and R are true</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only Q and R are true</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only P and Q are true</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Only R is true</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Only Q and R are true</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2083/gate2014-3-49#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Let S denote the set of all functions f:\\({\\{0,1\\}}^{4} \\rightarrow \\{0,1\\}\\). Denote by N the number of functions from S to the set {0,1}. The value of  \\(log_{2} log_{2}N\\) is______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "16",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1930/gate2014-1-50#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>How many onto (or surjective) functions are there from an n-element ( \\(n \\geq 2\\) ) set to a 2-element set? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(2^{n}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^{n}-1\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{n}-2\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2(2^{n}-2)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{n}-2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1759/gate2012-37#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(f\\) be a function from a set A to a set B,  \\(g\\) a function from B to C, and \\(h\\) a function from A to C, such that \\(h(a) = g(f(a))\\) for all \\(a \\in A\\). Which of the following statements is always true for all such functions \\(f\\) and \\(g\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>g is onto \\(\\implies h\\) is onto</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>h is onto \\(\\implies f\\) is onto</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>h is onto \\(\\implies g\\) is onto</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>h is onto \\(\\implies f\\) and g are onto</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>h is onto \\(\\implies g\\) is onto</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3777/gate2005-it-31\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Let f: B \\(\\rightarrow\\) C and g: A \\(\\rightarrow\\) B be two functions and let h = f\\(\\cdot\\)g. Given that h is an onto function which one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>f and g should both be onto functions</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>f should be onto but g need not to be onto</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>g should be onto but f need not be onto</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>both f and g need to be onto</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>f should be onto but g need not to be onto</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1168/gate2005-43#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Let : A\\(\\rightarrow\\)B be injective (one-to-one) function. <br><br>Define \\(g:2^{A}\\rightarrow 2^{B}\\) as: <br><br>\ng(C) = {f (x)| x \\(\\in\\)C), for all subsets C of A. <br><br>\nDefine\\(g:2^{B}\\rightarrow 2^{A}\\) as : <br><br> h(D) = {x | x \\(\\in\\) A, f (x) \\(\\in\\) D}, for all subsets D of B. <br><br>\nWhich of the following statements is always true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>g(h(D)) \\(\\subseteq\\)\n3D</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>g(h(D)) \\(\\supseteq\\) 4D</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>g(h(D)) \\(\\cap D=\\phi\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>g(h(D)) \\(\\cap (B-D)\\neq  \\phi\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>g(h(D)) \\(\\subseteq\\)\n3D</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/927/gate2003-37#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
